以下简称“哈勃”
哈勃太空望远镜可以说是这些年来性价比最高的科学工程了
The Hubble Space Telescope has been one of the most valuable scientific projects of recent times
有些人甚至认为我们从哈勃那里学到的比阿波罗的还多
Some even say that we've learned more with Hubble than we did with Apollo
但夕阳无限好，只是近黄昏
But like all good things it must come to an end
哈勃的大限已经离我们不远了
and that end will be coming in the not-too-distant future
以下简称“JWST”
不过它有个蓄势待发的后继者——詹姆斯·韦伯太空望远镜
But the Hubble has a successor waiting in the wings the James Webb Space Telescope
JWST基于哈勃成功的经验而制造
This builds on the success of the Hubble
又有21世纪最新技术的加持
but with 21st century technology
并承诺可以观测到更伟大的发现
and promises even greater discoveries
唯一的问题是它已经咕了14年了，预算也超了十倍
The only problem is that it's now 14 years late and about 10 times over budget
而且已经推迟到2021年才发射
and still won't be launched until 2021
所以为什么我们不能让哈勃无限连任？
So why can't we keep Hubble going?
JWST又为什么延期如此之久且造价如此之高呢？
And why is the JWST so late and so expensive
像JWST这类的工程经常会延期或者遇到各种问题
Big projects like the James Webb Space Telescope are often beset by delays and problems
包括哈勃也是这样
The Hubble itself is no stranger to controversy
哈勃于上世纪70年代设计，原定于1983年发射
designed in the 1970s it was due to be launched in 1983
但因技术问题、预算缩减和挑战者号的事故，它的发射延期了七年
But with technical issues, budget restrictions and the Challenger disaster it was delayed for seven years
到了天上以后发现当时全人类造的最完美的镜子
Only when it was in orbit did they find that the most perfectly ground mirror in history
还出现了形状上的偏差，说白了哈勃近视眼了
had been made with a tiny error in its shape effectively making it short-sighted
哈勃初期失焦的照片
后来又花了三年才终于算是把它修好
It took a further three years before a fix was created to finally get it working as it should
光学修正组件安装过程简易动画
哈勃本身设计就是可以在轨维护升级
The Hubble was designed to be serviced and upgraded in orbit
过去25年里它进行了5次维护
and over the last 25 years it has undergone five service missions
这些任务全部是由航天飞机完成的
This was all done using the Space Shuttle
并且在每次维护结束后，航天飞机都会把哈勃推向更高的轨道
and at the end of each mission the shuttle would move the Hubble to a higher orbit
这样做的目的在于，虽然哈勃望远镜是在太空中运行
This is done because although Hubble is in orbit in space
但它的轨道还是太低了，仍然能够触及大气最上层极其微薄的空气
the height of this orbit is still low enough to be in the very, very thin upper atmosphere
而这会产生阻力，逐渐降低其速度
And this creates drag which slows it down over time
速度慢了，轨道就会下降
This slowing down causes the orbit to decay and become lower
轨道下降，阻力又会变大，速度继续变慢
which increases the drag which slows it down more
进而继续下降，增加阻力……如此周而复始
which makes it come lower which increases the drag and so on and so forth
如果什么都不做，那它终将进入大气烧毁
And if nothing is done then eventually it will crash back to earth and burn up
2018年10月5日，哈勃在它的一个陀螺仪坏掉后进入了休眠模式
On October 5th 2018 Hubble went into sleep mode when one of its gyroscopes failed
陀螺仪作用是在轨调整并保持航天器姿态
These are devices which are used to help guide and keep its orientation in orbit
哈勃上有六个，坏了四个
And although it does have six, four have now failed
其中三个是旧款，这么长时间也该坏了，但这次坏的是新款
Three of the six were an older design and that was to be expected but this was one of the newer design ones
左侧鸟语：休眠7年多的备用陀螺仪本该被启动，却发现其工作异常。
但在使用了一种叫“重新启动”的古老技术后它又恢复正常了
虽说理想情况下需要三个来分别控制XYZ轴
Although it ideally needs three to operate one for each axis the X Y & Z
但新的操控技术使它可以只使用一个
new operational techniques mean that it can work with just one
作为哈勃维护任务的一部分
As part of the ongoing servicing of Hubble
新型陀螺仪和一堆其他设备在前几次任务中都装了上去
the newer design gyros along with a list of other equipment had been installed on a previous service mission
但毕竟都是机械设备，总有一天会出故障
but these are mechanical devices and as such they will wear out eventually
现在的问题是我们已经没有航天飞机去维护哈勃或者抬高其轨道了
The problem is we no longer have a space shuttle to do any further service missions or boost Hubble's orbit
所以即使一切运转正常
So even if nothing else goes wrong
哈勃也会在大约2028年到2040年之间落回地球
Hubble will eventually fall back to earth somewhere between 2028 and 2040
这个估计范围如此大是因为太阳活动会影响到地球外围大气的密度
This rather vague date is because it's the sun's activity that affects the expansion of the Earth's atmosphere
类似天宫一号
最终会影响到哈勃受到的大气阻力
and ultimately the atmospheric drag on Hubble
所以我们只能估计到这种程度
And that's something which we can only estimate into the future
但原本计划并非如此
But it wasn't planned to end like this
原定计划之一就是用航天飞机把哈勃再带回来
one of the scenarios was that the Hubble would be brought back to earth by the shuttle
放到类似美国国立博物馆之类的地方展出
and maybe placed somewhere like the Smithsonian Museum
要是说非要给它再续几年的话
If there is the political will Hubble's life could be extended
有种想法是用将来载人的追梦者飞船
there has been talk of a commercial mission using a manned version of a Dream Chaser
内华达山脉公司“追梦者号”飞船
去维护哈勃，并抬高它的轨道，以防万一——
to service Hubble and boost its orbit just in case
——万一JWST又双叒叕延期
there are further delays with the James Webb Space Telescope
甚至万一JWST变成了一百亿美元的烟花（我呸）
or god forbid but something happens to it during its launch
但不管怎么说，目前我们真的没有任何能把哈勃带回来的载具
But either way we now just don't have a vehicle that could bring the Hubble safely back to earth
回到JWST上，它又为什么连上天都这么费劲呢？
But why is the James Webb taking so long to quite literally get off the ground
原因之一是它的最终运行位置
Well one of the reasons is where it will take up its final position
和哈勃的540公里高的近地轨道不同
Unlike the Hubble which is just 540 kilometres above the earth
JWST将要绕日运行，距离地球150万千米
the James Webb will actually orbit the Sun 1.5 million kilometres away from Earth
位于地日第二拉格朗日点，即“L2点”
at the second LaGrange point or L2
在那个点，太阳、地球、月球的引力共同提供其绕日运行的向心力
where the gravitational effects of the Sun, the moon and the earth cancel each other out
在三个天体引力的共同作用下进入一个稳定轨道
and allow it to be in a stable orbit with regard to all three
这使得JWST的维修将和哈勃完全不同，一旦JWST出事
This means that fixing the James Webb unlike the Hubble if something were to go wrong
去它旁边维修几乎是不可能完成的任务
would range from be extremely difficult to the nigh on impossible
尤其是我们压根就没有能飞那么远的载人飞船
especially when we don't even have any manned spacecraft capable of traveling out that far
所以必须保证每个环节完美工作
So everything has to work perfectly
方法就是测试、测试²、测试³，甚至还要对测试进行测试
which means testing, testing and more testing and even testing the tests
当年哈勃的近视眼归根结底就是地面测试某环节出了问题
The memory of the Hubble Fiasco which was basically down to a failure of testing
这使得主承包商诺斯罗普·格鲁曼更是加倍小心
looms large in the minds of Northrop Grumman the primary contractor and the others involved
另一个问题就是，之前没人造过像JWST这样的东西
The other issue is that no one has built anything quite like the James Webb before
JWST的构想刚出现时，其中有至少十项科技点是人类还没有的
At the time of its conception at least ten of the technologies required had yet to be invented
比如网球场大的五层巨型遮光罩
Things like the giant five layer Sun shield for size of a tennis court
从折叠状态到完全部署展开需要整整两周
that will take two weeks to deploy from it's folded up form
它还不只是简单的一个有遮阳罩和控制系统的探测器
And it's not only the detectors for Sun shield and the control systems
它还要工作在只比绝对零度高几十度的超低温下
which will have to work at just a few degrees above absolute zero
高温侧
太阳帆板
通讯天线
计算机
动量轮与喷口
低温侧
科学仪器：
探测器与滤光器
镜面
JWST探测设备一侧必须保持非常低的温度
Everything on the detection side of a telescope must be as cold as possible
以降低极其微弱红外光干扰
so as not to interfere with the tiny amounts of infrared light
因为JWST探测的是来自宇宙最远处
that the James Webb is looking for from the farthest reaches of the universe
宇宙大爆炸初期星系的红外光
from the very first galaxies that formed after the Big Bang
极高敏感度的需求也使它拥有6.5米直径的主镜
This includes the mirror which are 6 and 1/2 meters across
光照面积是主镜直径2.4米的哈勃的6.25倍
has 6.25 times more light collecting area than Hubble which had a 2.4 meter mirror
单独一整块镜子的话太大了，装不进火箭整流罩
A single mirror this large wouldn't fit into any existing spacecraft
所以它由18块六边形镜面构成
so it's made up of 18 hexagonal sections
每一块都是独立控制，使其对焦到传感器上
which are individually controlled to focus for light onto the sensors
研发新技术、修BUG加上反反复复的测试这些全新的想法
Inventing the technologies, ironing out the bugs and the exhaustive testing of these brand-new ideas
耗费了大量时间与金钱
takes a lot of time and a lot of money
而这就是JWST咕到现在的另外一个主要原因
And this is the other main reason why is taking so long to get the Space Telescope ready
回到1996年，JWST还在构想之中时报价是10亿美元
Back in 1996 when the JWST was conceived the original price was $1 billion
并预计2007年发射
and it was expected to be launched around 2007
但实际上当时没人知道这望远镜怎么造，因此这个时间估计相当保守
But equally no one at the time actually knew how to build it and this was very much a best-guess estimate
据说NASA的这类项目都会估计的非常乐观
It's been said that NASA projects like this are often wildly optimistic
毕竟上来就狮子大开口的话谁也不敢掏钱
and are pitched low so as not to scare off potential funding
何况预算不够我们还可以再要
knowing that we can always go back and ask for more
但随着时间推移，JWST的制造难度逐渐显现，预算也水涨船高
But as time has gone by the difficulties have began to mount up and so did the costs
这使得NASA只能继续管国会老爷要钱，然后继续延期
This meant that NASA has to keep going back to Congress for more funding which took more time and delayed the whole project
这个轮回至今还在继续
This repeating process has now gone on and on until now
目前估计JWST总花销已直逼100亿刀
the total is expected to be just short of $10 billion
但政府那边难受在，假如这时候突然不给钱了
The problem for the government is that if it pulled the plug
那他们不但会少一个如此牛逼的望远镜
then not only will science be losing a highly anticipated tool
而且之前花的几十亿美刀也打水漂了
but they will have spent billions with nothing to show for it
这样还不如给钱造完
which in some ways would be worse
而从财政角度看也会认为这项工程也太失败了
and is also making the project almost too big to fail from a fiscal point of view
有些键盘侠认为造之前事先就该说好
Some commentators have said that it was all done backwards
用已有技术、一口价造完这望远镜
and that we should have built it with existing technologies which have an known price tag
可问题是，如果没有那些新技术的话，这望远镜根本就不存在啊
The problem with this argument is that it would have never been built
because we didn't have the technology to do so
更不可能无中生有出现一个专门造望远镜的某个技术出来
and waiting for someone to invent it without an end goal just isn't going to happen
如果键盘侠的理论放到阿波罗工程上，那人类根本不可能登上月球
If this methodology had been applied to Apollo we would have never gotten to the moon
所以有时我们会被报价所困扰
So we may well be stuck with a price tag
可NASA不也是为了竭尽所能防止JWST出故障嘛
but the least NASA can do now is try to eliminate as many of the possible points of failure as I can
这可以说是航天史上最谨慎的一个项目了
This is likely to become the most highly scrutinized project in space history so far
何况他们至少还有个安慰
but at least they can console themselves
因为和研发花费4000亿美元的F-35战机比起来，JWST简直是弟中弟
but it looks like an absolute bargain compared to the $400 billion
for the development of just one plane the F-35
所以你觉得哈勃的结局会怎样？修好还是受控坠毁？
So what do you think we should do with the Hubble fix it or leave it to a controlled reentry burn up
而你对JWST又有怎样的想法？欢迎在评论区留言
and what's your thoughts about the JWST? Let me know in the comments below
也记得看看我的其他视频（Youtube频道：Curious Droid）
And don't forget to check out some of our other videos
字幕翻译给虫，记得点赞投币收藏分享转发充电哦
and now it just remains for me to say thanks for watching and please subscribe, thumbs up and share